Will AIs ever be smarter than humans? It
&gt;&gt; depends what you mean by smarter. Of
course, a pocket calculator is smarter
than a human in in many important ways.
But uh in u if you're talking about um
some software being able to emulate all
functions of the human mind and do that
better than humans,
then I think uh the first is possible.
but nowhere near as far as I can tell
and the second is impossible. So they
will never be fundamentally better
though they may be faster
but uh then the that will only be
because they are running on faster
hardware and that faster hardware will
have been invented by humans for humans
in the first instance. So we can be
faster as well and in fact we are being
faster at this very moment than
than uh before this technology was
invented.
uh you know we would have had to
communicate by email and before that we
would have had to communicate by snail
mail and before that actual snails
&gt;&gt; distant ancestors
&gt;&gt; quite
&gt;&gt; correct me if I'm wrong but the reason
you have this conclusion is because
computers can do or anything that can do
computation including the human brain
has a kind of repertoire of which
programs it can execute and there are
some very simple computers like a
calculator which is quite limited in its
repertoire of what it can calculate. But
then Turing showed in well you will have
to remind me what year
&gt;&gt; this idea of a 96
&gt;&gt; 36 [laughter]
&gt;&gt; this idea of a universal touring machine
which was a hypothetical machine that
could perform any computation that you
could even uh imagine being able to
perform. And it's trivial to show that
humans are a universal Turing machine
because we can execute with pen and
paper the the simple universal Turing
machine that Turing originally
envisaged. So this shows that our
repertoire of programs that we can
execute is fundamentally the same as any
other universal touring machine whether
that be an AGI or another human being.
Have I understood that correctly?
&gt;&gt; Yes. There is the other half of although
we can emulate a touring machine um can
we emulate any any other machine or is
there some machine that's beyond the
touring machine and that is a question
of physics not mathematics and that
proving that follows from quantum theory
is something that I did in the 1980s
&gt;&gt; so your theorem said something like any
physical process not just a computation
but any physical process can be emulated
on a would it require a quantum
&gt;&gt; process that obeys quantum theory? Yes.
&gt;&gt; I see. And would that require a quantum
computer to emulate or just a computer?
A classic
&gt;&gt; for some things it would require a
quantum computer although a quantum
computer itself can be emulated
classically
given an exponentially large slowdown.
&gt;&gt; I see. [laughter]
So that that might become a bit of a
hindrance for some tasks.
&gt;&gt; It it would. Yes. Um but on the other
hand um if you're thinking about AGI
outperforming humans by having a quantum
computer at its disposal well as as I
said before when that technology exists
then humans will also have quantum
computers at their disposal.
&gt;&gt; Mhm. I think we'll have to leave quantum
computing aside because it's well far
out my my wheelhouse. [laughter]
So let's let's stick to classical
computation for the moment.
&gt;&gt; Um I so I completely agree that we have
the same repertoire being universal
touring machines. But I think there's
something extra that determines whether
someone succeeds at a problem whereas
someone else might fail at solving a
problem or take much longer. So, for
example, if I'm playing Magnus Carlson
at chess, it is theoretically true that
I can simulate all of the computations
going on in his brain given enough time
and enough pen and paper. But when I
come to play Magnus Carlson, he will
still beat me at chess. So, I'm worried
we could end up in a similar situation
with AIS where even if their repertoire
is the same, the speed at which they
compute uh means they'll be able to run
rings around us.
again uh what you say is true of
existing computers and is again
happening all the time but the um
example of Magnus Carlson is is a bit
misleading because we don't know what
the program is that
&gt;&gt; Magnus Carlson is executing and it's the
&gt;&gt; uh it's inconceivable that he is that
much better than all the other
professional chess players because of
hardware.
In fact, the the the only way in which
hardware can help you is with speed or
memory capacity.
&gt;&gt; And uh the um as I said, it's beyond
belief that Magnus Carlson differs from
the others by that much, especially
software.
And that [clears throat] is is um a
program
uh in his um brain in his mind which he
constructed
um for himself uh to meet his
preferences his problem situation
and that is what we are playing against.
You know we people sometimes say I had a
game of chess against the computer
yesterday but that's never true. You're
you're playing chess against a program
and uh when you're you're playing Magnus
Carlson, you're also playing the program
in his mind and it's that that's
amazing, not his brain.
&gt;&gt; Yes. Our brains are basically the same
architecturally,
&gt;&gt; far as we know. Yes.
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. Um so there there's there's
this difference in software and also
this potential difference in speed with
AIS. And one of the things you mentioned
at least for speed and memory capacity
is that if future AIs, AGIS, whatever
do far exceed us on um speed and memory,
then at the same time we'll also have
computers uh that can aid us in uh
memory and speed. My my question then is
um
how would we make sure that that
computer that's aiding us is sort of on
our side as it were and it it's willing
to do our bidding.
&gt;&gt; Oh well the computer isn't going to be
an AGI any more than the computer that
the AGI uses is an AGI.
&gt;&gt; The AGI is the program. The person is
the program and we use hardware which is
uh just dumb computer compute as they
call it uh both in our brain and in our
computers and in future computers. So
the AGI will have uh will be using a
computer that isn't an AGI. It it may
seem paradoxical this but but of course
every computer program consists of
subprograms
that do not have the property of the
overall program.
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
&gt;&gt; Just like um u the creativity of
um natural selection and evolution
consists of things that are not natural
selection and evolution. adaptations
consists of things which aren't
adaptations and so on.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; So we we just use the physical world
including computers
&gt;&gt; to um do the non
nonperson
uh computations for us.
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I could you paint a picture of
what that would look like? cuz at the
moment when I think of augmenting my uh
my abilities with a computer, part of it
to do with um sort of dumb a AI, non
Aadi AI uh that can do calculations
quickly or could uh could play chess for
me against Magnus Carlson in order to
beat [clears throat] him.
&gt;&gt; That's the fundamentally creative parts.
um it seems a lot harder to offload that
to an AI without encountering
a a problem of control, a problem that
it's still doing what what you want it
to do.
&gt;&gt; Yes, that's that's because um the
offloading that you're thinking of
is offloading the creative part of your
mind and that that part is extremely
small compared with the capacity of your
brain.
when when if I ask you now, you know, um
what did you vote at the last election
and why and you have to think in panic
of how you can not tell me um then the
the part of your brain that is doing
that computation that creative
computation is a tiny part. Most of your
brain is is um well I I I don't know of
course but I think that most of our
brains consist of data that is memories
which are not active. Some of it
consists of
um the initiation of uh of a creative
computation that is not currently active
and then there's the creative part which
is currently active which can't possibly
be more than a tiny proportion of that.
We are not limited
when we are creative. We are not limited
by our hardware except in the sense that
if we didn't have a pocket calculator,
we'd be also limited. But but in in the
creative part of our thinking,
uh it it's not that I would be able to
think of quantum gravity if only I had a
few more brain cells or if I had twice
the number of brain cells or if two
people are working on it. That that's
not how it works. It it it
[clears throat] is in in quality
not quantity that the creative
program differs from the rest of the
program in the brain. The rest of the
data in the brain, the rest of the bra
data that we have in our computers, it's
all of a different kind to that one kind
that we don't know how to characterize,
but we know what it does.
Do I understand correctly then that
you're saying something like um that we
would offload onto the computer the
drudge work whereas the creativity
there's no need to offload that because
we're already sufficiently creative.
We're not hardware constrained by that.
&gt;&gt; And so having an AI that was also being
creative just simply isn't necessary in
order to to meet our goals.
&gt;&gt; Yes. Um, for what it's worth, I mean, I
don't know if he knew any more than we
do, but but Turing
uh thought that the the creative program
could fit into two megabytes.
So, uh, I I [clears throat]
see no reason why that shouldn't be
true. I mean, I I I I know of nothing
in what we know of what creativity,
human creativity does that suggests it
has to be much bigger than that. Of
course, our memory has to be much much
bigger than that.
&gt;&gt; I suppose when when I'm trying to solve
a problem, let's take a a maths problem
for example, and I'm coming up with
conjectures for for how to prove prove a
theorem. Um, I think, okay, let's try
induction. H, what variable should we
try inducting on?
&gt;&gt; Then it takes me quite a long time to
come up with these conjectures. And if I
were able to offload that program that
conjectures uh the program that comes up
with the conjectures for me onto some
hardware that could run the same program
but faster then it would come up with
conjectures more quickly and so it would
make progress more quickly. So I'm not
quite sure I see that we would only need
in order to keep up with an AI we would
only need to offload the drudge work
onto a computer. So now you're talking
about only about speed because you're
kind of agreeing that that the memory
capacity is not a relevant constraint.
Although you could ask what about the
distant future when we've improved our
creativity so much that it really does
take up terabytes.
Let let's let's not deal with that for
the moment. So now you're just talking
about speed. Well, for speed, um, just
as we we have learned how to
code, we've learned how to program, and
now we're all learning how to um set up
prompts for the um LLMs that we deal
with.
&gt;&gt; Uh, so we have all learned in our
childhood how to set up prompts and code
for our own creativity.
Like when you say shall we do it by
induction and and well which variable
then
&gt;&gt; enumerating the variables that you could
do that you could do that with is
already a non-creative task.
So a non um creative AI could be trained
to do that. you would be in a constant
dialogue with it because as as soon as
you said maybe induction it would
already come up with six or seven kinds
of induction and if we had an AGI that
could do that then if it wanted to
that's another problem with thinking
about AGIs being our slaves. If it
wanted to, it could try six or seven of
those and say, "Well, the seventh one
seems seems most most prom promising.
Shall I try that?" And then I could say,
"Yeah, try that." And it would say, "No,
I want to play chess." [laughter]
[clears throat]
&gt;&gt; So, I suppose it if you're offloading
onto an AGI, then then we surely do get
this problem of um control uh or you
would call it enslavement. Um, and I'm
not sure I would disagree with that. Um,
but I if we are
just suppose for a moment that we are in
an adversarial relationship with some AI
and we're trying to keep up with it,
then um
I I I do find myself struggling to
believe that we could be creative as
quickly as efficiently as it could if it
was running the same program at 10 times
the speed or thousand times that speed.
uh again
uh I I think all your questions so far
have been of the form let's not compare
like with like [laughter] so I I think I
I think
uh if you want to do that sort of
comparison
then compare yourself with
the British government. The British
government consists of I don't know
hundreds of thousands of people and
they're working on problems uh some of
which are the same as the problem you're
working on and uh they're not uh
necessarily going to solve it faster
than you just because there's 100,000 of
them. That's because a 100,000 of them
um are not coordinated.
If they were coordinated, that would be
a bad thing.
So, um, that that would mean that that
they're wasting most of their creativity
because their creativity consists of
ways in which they are different
rather than ways in which they are the
same.
So there if if you want better
creativity,
having faster or more voluminous
creativity isn't the way to go. It's if
if you if you have um an an AGI, it
would be much better to make it do
lots of ci creative tasks in parallel
than one in series
because then it it will gain the
benefit. But then
um if you have if you make your computer
into a thousand AGIS or a million AGIS
then
these are a million people. They will
have property. Each one of them will
have property because they will be
working for a living and they'll be
earning their hardware and they'll be
earning their electricity and uh they
will be earning the uh laboratories in
which they do experiments and so on and
so it's it's they will not want to
duplicate themselves
um too often because they will have to
share their resources and uh that is
exactly the
thing that constrains the number of
humans.
So we have the number of humans is 8 and
a half billion or whatever it is. Um
basically the reason why it's not 80 and
a half is that we haven't worked out how
to have enough resources for all of them
to live good lives and to and to be able
to devote time to solving creative
problems.
So,
um, by the way, we're talking here about
something much further into the future
than merely the advent of AGI,
&gt;&gt; which itself, I I would guess is fairly
far in the future, but but um um so uh
yes, it will be a different kind of
culture. the maybe there will come a
time when most people are
AGIS
um and we'll be able to upload ourselves
into an AGI into a computer to make an
AGI you know maybe we'll upload
ourselves in the morning and go back to
our human bodies in the afternoon or or
something like that we we can't foretell
what kind of what kind of relationship
we'll have with these minds
but um that we don't want them
to be alike. We don't want them to be
subordinate to us any more than we want
all other humans to be subordinate to us
or any other humans to be subordinate to
us. We if there's one thing we've
learned in politics in the last few
hundred years is that a society is more
efficient,
more creative when its people are
individuals than when they're all
subordinated to a single goal.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I think I'm happy with AGIS being
uh on a level footing with humans in
terms of rights uh and property and uh
their place in society. But I would want
to first be sure that one that they
share at least the core values uh that
we've developed um in order to maintain
progress of civilization and and not
blow ourselves up and and also that if
their values do diverge, they're not
able to run way ahead of us. Um, now I
think I'm not
I'm not quite following your argument
and that's almost certainly my fault um
of why they wouldn't be able to run
ahead of us. I suppose
that we we'll discuss the values later,
but suppose it did have and AGI did have
values that diverged from ours. Um
suppose the world hangs on who wins a
chess game for example
then um well but that's a bad example
cuz it doesn't create require a huge
amount of creativity. You could get
there with raw compute power. Let's
suppose it it required coming [snorts]
up with some new technology some new
weapon that would um be able to
disempower the other side. And then it's
a battle between humans and these AIs
with divergent values as to who develops
this kind of technology first. Could you
spell out for me why it wouldn't be the
case that an AGI with just a similar
program to what a human's running, but
running 10,000 times the speed, wouldn't
just get to that technology first and
then disempower us with it?
Well, I think 10,000 times the speed is
um
uh is not the right way to think about
it because if it had 10,000 creativity
modules, then they wouldn't all be
working on the same thing or if they
were they'd be they'd have formed some
kind of totalitarian society. And that
that
possibility is with us now. This this is
the problem that humans have been trying
to solve for 30,000 years or ever since
we formed communities at all. We have
the problem that different communities
are going to have different values and
we'll will if if we don't arrange the
memes properly, they will fight each
other
&gt;&gt; and it won't always be the the more
creative ones who win. Um but it but if
it's not the most creative ones who win
then everybody suffers including the
less creative ones.
So or or um we the the society that we
call the west has solved that problem on
a coarse grain scale. That is we still
have people like murderers. We still
have people who fall for um um
anti-rational fads and and violent fads
and so on. But we have arranged it so
that the in the west the societies
themselves don't go to war and the
societies are capable of suppressing
uh rogue elements of their own society.
Um there are people are wondering at the
moment whether some aspects of that
peaceful
dispensation are breaking down at the
moment but they have and we can't we
can't tell for sure. We can't prophesy.
Maybe they are going to break down. But
there's no more
evidence of that now than than certainly
than 50 years ago or 100 years ago. On
the face of it, things were a lot worse
100 years ago.
&gt;&gt; Uh but in societies outside the west,
uh they haven't solved that. They
haven't come close yet to solving that
problem. and and the West has tried all
sorts of ways of of uh trying to
show them that it's better to have this
new peaceful way of interacting with
each other and with and with the West
and uh it's it's succeeded a few times
but it has failed many more times.
So we don't know how to do this and we
uh if
you begin your hypothesis by saying
suppose there are rogue AGIS who are set
on creating violence and destroying our
society or destroying us physically then
they will
um if there are enough of them you know
we we might have maybe the good guys
have an inherent advantage up to a
factor of eight but if then [laughter]
if there's a factor of 80 Then
although well I don't know I I'm I'm
just wondering whether
eight normal grandmasters
are better than one Magnus Carlson.
Uh I think not.
&gt;&gt; Um so
&gt;&gt; probably not. There was this experiment
a number of years ago, Gary Casparov
versus the world, where uh the rest of
the rest of the world played by voting
on moves, and part of the world team
were four grand masters um who were
there to try and advise on on the voting
system. And Gary Kasparov still won, but
he did spoil the experiment by reading
the forum where they were discussing
their moves. [laughter]
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. Um Yeah. So I but but in
principle such a thing could win against
humans. But then the problem of that
problem is just a the same problem we
have now
writ small because if we in the west
make a ais they're going to have to be
educated. They're going to have to
acquire culture. Again, it's no good
making one with culture and then
duplicating it many times because then
you'll lose most of the advantage as
I've said of having more than one.
&gt;&gt; So, uh there will be a population of
AGIS
uh who are growing up. They are they
basically children, teenagers, young
people who are growing up and if they
don't grow up with our culture then it's
we who are to blame, not them. Um so but
but we we know how to propagate our
culture. So it should be a soluble
problem.
&gt;&gt; Well, we know how to propagate it to
other humans.
&gt;&gt; Well, there there is no difference. The
people are people.
&gt;&gt; Uh what do you mean by a person?
&gt;&gt; It's somebody who is capable of
explanatory creativity.
&gt;&gt; And why does that the thing we're
talking about? The thing that causes the
G in AGI. Yes. Um I mean you could be
capable of coming up with creative
explanations about some things but not
others.
&gt;&gt; I think not because the the method of
creating creative explanations is
independent of the subject.
Um it it's I mean you know there wasn't
a module for general relativity waiting
30,000 years or 300,000 years [laughter]
for Einstein to come along and finally
use that module. He used the same kind
of thinking as our ancestors used to to
build the first campfire.
&gt;&gt; Sure. I mean in morality there is kind
of an inbuilt module which is our own
qualia, our own sensory experiences of
of what's fun and what's not, what's
enjoyable and what's what counts as
suffering. And it's possible that AIs
wouldn't share that same bedrock, that
same module.
&gt;&gt; Yeah. But it's not bedrock. And it's the
same issue because um different people
greatly differ on what counts as
qualia that they want to aim for and
qualia that they do not want to aim for.
So um I I'm sitting in Oxford here uh
not very far from here. Archbishop
Cranmer stuck his hand in the fire uh
because it was the hand that signed
whatever it was that that he now
regretted and he was going to be burnt
at the stake and so on and and so he
stuck his hand in the fire. I I uh
apparently that's historically uh rock
solid. He really did do it and there are
people who set fire to themselves. Um
[snorts] so and there are people who
starve themselves to death. Um so or
drown themselves. Uh so we are
one of the things that has evolved
between when we were
just AIS or you know apes and when our
ape ancestors became people.
uh is the ability to to disregard the
the criteria
um inherited by through genes from our
ancestors.
&gt;&gt; So we we inherited uh an aversion to
fire. Uh we couldn't have made uh
campfires if we hadn't been able to over
override that not override is the wrong
word. set aside that aversion in favor
of curiosity and hope and and problem
solving and all the things that were
important to our ancestors. They were
able to set that aside. Uh so to set
their sorry to set their um aversion to
fire aside.
Um so uh the the um
in in short per I'm making to heavy
weather of this but in short I don't
think the qualia determine our thinking
they they are raw material for our
thinking and we could provide similar
raw material. Maybe that's one of the
things that's needed for AGI. We don't
know. Maybe they they they could only be
robots with artificial senses and
artificial pain and so on. But uh that's
not going to determine whether they are
good or bad people. Whether they are
good or bad people is going to be
determined by their creative solving of
moral problems beginning with the
problem of what do I do now.
&gt;&gt; I think it's maybe worth distinguishing
the idea of good and bad versus simply
different values. I think it's possible
that I mean suppose we had um alien
contact and the aliens could be
perfectly nice people to each other. Uh
except they just have very very
different values to us. Um and it's not
therefore they would be dangerous to us
and we would be dangerous to them. Not
because either of us are more evil than
the other, just because we have
different values, different desires for
what to do with uh well, what's around
us, how to steer the future, and that
alone would put us into conflict without
saying that anyone is fundamentally
worse than the other. Well, uh I I think
that if we do encounter aliens in that
way, which I think is very unlikely
given the distances involved, but if if
we do, I think it's very much on the
cards that we will have different
values,
&gt;&gt; but it's uh inconceivable to me that the
that
we couldn't resolve this the same way
that we attained our present values,
which are extremely different from what
our values were a thousand years ago and
that was different from what they were
10,000 years ago. Uh they will they
would probably be a million millions of
years ahead of us and presumably more
moral than us. I I would think one of
the things that happens with the growth
of knowledge is that um uh solving
problems sometimes causes a jump to
universality.
So uh we and this happened in regard to
morality in our early prehistory when
people started uh thinking not just
what's good for my tribe but what is
actually good. There's the the ethifro
dialogue of Plato where where he says
are the are the gods um do the gods want
to do good because
um that's what good is. it's what the
gods want or is it because there's
something other than the gods that
something objective
where it's meaningful to say and it's
it's also in the uh it's in the Hebrew
Bible when when Abraham
rebukes God and says something like is
the person who uh is the person who um
gives us morality not subject to
morality some something like that. So
&gt;&gt; they're already thinking that and the
fact that they're thinking that shows
that some previous time people weren't
thinking about that. They they they were
thinking in a much more narrow way and
to get to the objective morality idea.
They got to it by trying to improve
their values or or rather by trying to
solve their problems by improving their
values.
So, so that's what they did and that
that's what you know if we were several
million years apart or whatever we would
have to do that in spades with the with
the aliens [laughter]
that's again that's good
&gt;&gt; um I suppose there's one question of
would we talk it out uh it's it's
possible that they just wouldn't be
bothered to talk it out uh I mean
historically
some Human cultures have not always been
motivated to talk it out with other
cultures. They've just colonized and
suppressed.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, it it does happen, but it it
happens less often than than you're
making out. Um, you know, Genghis Khan
may be may be an example of someone who
just conquered. But people like the
Romans, the Romans always wanted an
excuse for when to invade someone.
So, so the fact that they wanted an
excuse means that they they um had an
idea that that um they wanted to think
of themselves as people who act morally
according to a code. And uh there's the
before that there's the Athenians in the
Pelipenian war who conquered this island
um Milos or something. The Melian
dialogue is is when um uh they are
reputed to have said um uh the strong do
what they can and the weak endure what
they must. M
&gt;&gt; and [clears throat]
but you see they had to say that that
that was a pathetic justification
of what they wanted to do despite the
fact that they knew there were moral
arguments against it. Maybe they thought
that there were other moral arguments in
favor of it in that situation. But even
in those days when it was quite normal
to to if if a place didn't
um uh surrender, if a city didn't
surrender, then then when you later
conquered it, you would kill all the men
and take the women and children into
slavery. That was normal, but it wasn't
universal even then.
So, um people thought about what was
better. And while they were thinking not
very good ideas about what was better,
they didn't make so much progress. They
started making very rapid progress at a
time when they allowed
their moral theories to be subject to
the same error correction type process
as as their scientific theories and and
their astronomical theories and all
their other theories.
And and it's not it's not an accident
that they came to converge.
um different moral theories came to
converge.
&gt;&gt; The the the different polities
within the uh enlightenment countries
within the west came came to converge
slowly.
They did have wars but they had fewer
and fewer wars and now they're having no
wars among themselves.
they could converge because through
an exploration of what they think is
morally true leads to them to what is
objectively morally true that that there
are actual errors that they actually
eliminate. But it could also be the case
that uh societies that um
manage to construct moral theories true
or not that allow them to cooperate uh
are more successful. So, it could it
could be the case that how do I want to
say this? I I I could well believe that
this this alien civilization could
engage in moral dialogue with us and yet
simply come to different conclusions
because there's no objective moral truth
that's sort of pushing us both towards
the same thing.
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I mean, it's pulling
[laughter] because we're looking for it.
So, one of one of the things you can do
when solving a a problem, you you can
you can narrow the problem and say,
well, can I solve this for the moment
and never mind the general case? Or you
can say, what would the general case
look like? How does how does can can we
can we import a problem from somewhere
else and apply it to this case? And when
when we do then we naturally wonder is
there something in common between these
two cases. And so people say the same
thing about laws of physics. You know
may maybe maybe
the the aliens have have the physics
which is completely different from ours.
So that for them they can travel faster
than light because uh they they conceive
of the world in such a different way
that they can build machines that can
travel faster than light and they never
they kind of went round our problem with
a finite speed of light and arrived
somewhere else um where we haven't got
to or or now I I think that's that's um
that requires a kind of conspiracy in
the laws of nature.
uh for there to be two solutions to
&gt;&gt; things like how does light behave uh
which are not visible to each other. And
with morality
it is much more so because with moral
with the with physics it's just a with
with fundamental physics anyway it's
just a question of how can we understand
the world being one way or rather than
another way. But with morality, it's how
can we do things such that we align with
other people who are doing things and so
on. So the idea that our morality should
be compatible with with the thought what
would I do if I was them
um it's it's become second nature to us.
It must become second nature to anyone
else who's been doing this especially
for a million years.
Let let me ask a couple more questions
to see if I can get this idea in my head
in my head. Um, when we're when we're
thinking about scientific theories and
trying to understand the world, the
world gets to bite back and chop off
some of our bad hypotheses. Uh, for you
you come up with some scientific theory,
it makes a prediction, you test it, and
you don't get the predictions you you
thought you would, and therefore that
theory is gone. It's eliminated. What's
the equivalent in morality where reality
bites back and shaves off uh your bad
hypothesis?
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Well, there is there is exactly
the same phenomenon in morality, but
with the morality, we've got more. So,
let me say where where it's the same is
if you've got a a rock star who um
starts earning millions of pounds and uh
starts being able to indulge his wildest
dreams and to have groupies on tap uh
every day and and finds that he's
getting less and less happy.
&gt;&gt; Uh he's got a moral problem. It's not
that he's failing to uh stimulate the
the same hormones
uh or something that that would have
been there when when he was poor. It's
that he realizes that he didn't act what
he actually wanted was not to increase
the level of those hormones. It was
something else which he has to
creatively think, creatively
um
um construct
so as to
be better
be better in a way that was not defined
by his previous self.
And that that uh so that's a moral
problem. And if he fails to solve it
then he will run into practical
u problems as well. But the you know as
I said the the practical thing is is is
more immediate with with the morality
than it is with physics. You you can go
along believing the Copenhagen
interpretation for decades and nothing
will happen to you.
&gt;&gt; Right?
But but if you if you believe that that
u morality consists of pursuing physical
pleasure at everything else's expense
then you will find out much faster.
Um so now there's also the theoretical
side of of morality which again you
could call it meta morality. It's kind
of uh theories about how to improve
moral theories. We we have the same
thing in physics. The theories of how
the the idea of that everything should
come down to testing
is quite new. It it's
no older than Galileo and in some sense
no older than papa to make to make that
the prime uh principle. Um and uh the
like I said the idea of you know how
should I behave towards this other
person? Well um because my morality is
is conflicting with his morality. Well
what if I was him? What would I think
then?
Um should I want him to think like I'm
thinking now and so on. And that that's
like like a natural thing or at least it
seems natural to us now. Um maybe the
the golden rule uh had a had the
beginnings of that a couple of thousand
years ago but the golden rule was hailed
as something new at the time. So before
that they didn't have that. So the these
are theoretical advances in morality
um and and they can they can be made.
There's no there's never a guarantee
that we will find the right answer. So
it could be that we will be destroyed
through not be able not being able to
make moral advances
&gt;&gt; next year or in the next generation
where there's never a guarantee but nor
is there
doom on the horizon.
&gt;&gt; So let let me let me investigate both of
those points. So I think the first one
you said was the the way in which
reality can bite back on your false
moral theories or conjectures is if you
pursue a moral theory of how to live a
good life or how to treat other people
and at the end of that you find yourself
not actually very happy and not very
satisfied then that means that that
theory is going to get rejected by you.
&gt;&gt; Well uh it won't get rejected until you
have a better one.
&gt;&gt; Right. you you will you will have to
creatively either try to tinker with it
and improve it or go to another theory
or tinker with someone else's theory or
you know like get religion or whatever.
&gt;&gt; Uh
&gt;&gt; so if you
&gt;&gt; it it seems possible that you could have
that that reality won't bite back in the
same way for different people. For some
people or agis or aliens pursuing a
moral theory will leave them happy and
satisfied. And for others such as AGIS,
it won't leave them happy or satisfied.
So why do we expect some convergence
there on on moral theories?
&gt;&gt; Well, because because none of us even
the rockstar
are actually driven by their qualia or
by [clears throat] their hormones or by
their DNA.
&gt;&gt; They they are always driven by trying to
solve problems. That that's what people
are. And sometimes they think that
solving the problem is behaving in a
certain way in order to get certain
sensations or whatever. But that's just
a theory. And as a theory, it's it's
very crude. And it it's not actually
true. And the reason why this rockstar
doesn't find that it's true for him is
that it's not true. In fact, uh it's not
true for anybody, even for aliens.
Um so so uh as I said we will have
different theories from aliens
&gt;&gt; but it won't be because we have
different nervous systems. Uh
&gt;&gt; I mean I could imagine an agent for whom
the rockstar's conjecture of how to live
a good life does does work for them
right?
&gt;&gt; Uh I I don't think so because because
the rockstar's criterion is is empty. It
doesn't require creativity to implement
it. So,
&gt;&gt; okay.
&gt;&gt; So, uh it's it's not going to sat it's
not going to satisfy any human to be in
that state.
&gt;&gt; I need to think about this. [laughter]
Um
&gt;&gt; quite exactly.
&gt;&gt; So, the second point you mentioned was
metamorality. How to improve moral
theories.
Um I'm afraid I can't remember the point
you made made on on that one. Is there
any chance you could repeat that bit?
&gt;&gt; Um I forgotten the question I was
answering but I was saying that part of
uh moral improvement is improve not only
improving moral theories but improving
moral meta theories. So just as we learn
to do better science both by by thinking
uh you know what might cause things to
fall rather than rise up in the air and
by thinking that maybe the difference
maybe the way to go is to in have two
two or more hypotheses about that and
test the difference. And when Galileo
did that with balls rolling down an
inclined plane,
um he was he had solved some meta
problem first because it he had to get
the idea that he could solve the problem
about things falling by solving the the
analogist problem with things rolling
down an inclined plane. That's not at
all obvious. In fact, I'm not I'm not
really sure that it's entirely true, but
it was true enough for for him to to to
make progress in his theories of inertia
and forces and so on. So, uh people who
didn't have the idea of testing theories
couldn't have made that progress that
Galileo made in physics.
So, they they they were deficient in
philosophy of physics.
And then what would be the analogy for
meta morality?
Um well we so my example if I remember
correctly maybe it's not a very good
example is is the the um trick of
putting yourself in the other person's
shoes
&gt;&gt; saying well uh well first of all saying
thinking um what I want is a theory of
morality not a theory of this morality
about what to do about campfires but a
theory of what to do in general h how
does one decide what to do. And then
there's the idea of well, one way is to
say supposing I had his theories and he
had my theories, what would happen?
Yeah, I think this is a good
I think that kind of meme uh that
technique has survived because it is
important to us in order to achieve what
we want to get along with other agents
and and to to make sure we can we can
live in a way that's that's compatible.
No, that's only part of the answer
because um uh for
for hundreds of thousands of years
humans used to beat their children and
uh in the last century that has tailed
off drastically. And it wasn't because
we needed to uh find a way of life uh
where we can where we can agree with our
children. it it's because we thought it
was wrong. And we thought it was wrong
because we have very general theories
about how to deal with other people.
Now, um in in the West, rationality and
and uh the there's there's just the idea
in in the West there's the idea that
that we can be mistaken and that the
good way of life is to not prevent the
correction of errors. Therefore, we
should judge, we should regard disputes
between people as being disputes between
their theories rather than between the
people.
&gt;&gt; And that [clears throat] has fed into
different ways of treating children,
different ways of treating animals,
different ways of treating women,
um different ways of treating
foreigners, uh uh different ways of
treating enemies.
uh it's all it's all part of the same
thing that that it's really the ideas
that that should be in conflict which
means that the criteria can't be
dependent on the substrate in which the
ideas are instantiated.
Mhm.
&gt;&gt; So I I I do buy that AGIS could do moral
thinking. Uh they could come up with
moral conjectures and criticism just
like we can and that follows simply from
universality.
Um
the question then would be
let let's leave aside the question of
whether they would come to the same
conclusions or follow the same kind of
meta morality metamoral processes.
Uh would the AGI
be motivated to apply its creative
conjecturing ability and criticism to
the domain of morality? Maybe it would
see it just as any other domain like
chemistry or physics or mathematics and
it thinks ah mathematics is not that
interesting. I do it when when I need
to. And morality yeah not super keen on
that. I do it when I need to.
&gt;&gt; Yes. Well, that's a moral theory
and it it it's uh it's not unknown for
people to adopt that moral theory and
it's a bad moral theory that leads to
disaster. [laughter]
What disaster does it lead to?
&gt;&gt; Um, well, it's like it's it's an example
is the rock star I imagined.
&gt;&gt; Um, so he he he he might say, well, I'm
interested in music. I'm interested in
um, you know, gratification.
Uh, I'm not terribly interested in
morality. You know, I have some
morality, but I'm not interested in
improving it. And uh you have if you
have a problem that your
existing morality is wrong, then you're
going to have no choice but to think
about it. Well, you have a choice of
thinking about it or being steeped in
error and and encountering disaster. And
the the disaster need not be that you
are destroyed or or starved to death or
anything. It could be just that um
you're sitting there with tears rolling
down your face with the lights dimmed
and you don't know what to do because uh
something in your mind has has decided
that
a range of possible thoughts are not
going to be thought because you are not
the kind of person that thinks that
those thoughts. That can happen. It
happens to people all the time and it it
it happens to people much more often
when there are when they've succumbed to
anti-rational memes than simply making a
series of mistakes. I mean, I think
making a series of mistakes is a rare
um cause of disaster.
Um unless the first one kills you or
something. Um but but mostly when people
make um chronic mistakes, it's because
of anti-rational memes. So that that
their creativity is devoted to
preventing criticism of a certain type
of theory in their minds. M
&gt;&gt; um
&gt;&gt; uh that that sort of some people think
of the enlightenment as the rebellion
against that kind of theory, the
rebellion against that kind of but we we
if if it's a rebellion against those we
we haven't succeeded yet. we we've only
kind of half succeeded and we're in a
we're in a intermediate state where
there's still a lot of anti-rational
memes about but um
uh but the the major
determinants of what happens in society
have turned largely to rational memes
that they're not perfect but at least
rational so they can be improved.
Mhm. Mhm. So, we we've gone down this
this route of of morality, metamorality.
Um, which is very interesting and I'm
not super qualified to [laughter]
investigate it properly. So, part of me
wonders,
&gt;&gt; I'm definitely,
&gt;&gt; but part of me wonders,
are we actually hitting on a crux here
of of the risks of AI if if you perceive
them or or not? For example, if it did
turn out to be the case that you could
have two agents, two GIS perfectly
capable of creative thought in every
domain. Well, it's only possible to be
in every domain. Um,
&gt;&gt; yeah. Then suppose you had these two
agents and yet even if they investigated
morality they still did not converge on
any kind of moral truth either because
moral truth doesn't exist or because uh
it's simply not the case that these
these mechanisms will or yeah a second
possibility would be that the kind of
conclusions you come to when thinking
about morality meta meta morality are in
fact highly dependent on your qualia. uh
suppose then if that was the case would
you then be worried about AI risk or
have we gone down a rabbit hole here
that's not really a crux
&gt;&gt; well uh
I I don't think
I mean yes that that is a crux if you
like I I I I would be wrong in that case
&gt;&gt; but but [clears throat]
I don't [laughter] think I I I haven't
explained to you quite how wrong I would
be if if if that were true um Because it
it would mean that there's something
there's something other than
computation,
some deep fact about mathematics or
about about uh the physical world that
prevents certain type of ideas from
existing in certain hardware.
What is it about the hardware? I mean
are are you imagining two machines with
the same hardware that end up
fundamentally opposed in this way or is
it just machines with different
hardware? If it's with the same hardware
then obviously the difference between
them is software. If it's with different
hardware then remember that each side
can simulate the other. So we can if if
we if we can't if we can't understand
why
the AGI thinks that a certain thing is
right and we think it's wrong, we can
still
simulate it. we can simply work out the
problem as it sees it and and see why
it's coming with the to the conclusion
that it came to and then we can say ah
yes it's because but then I don't see
how that can happen because there it's
as if there were two different kinds of
information in the world
&gt;&gt; and we as one
&gt;&gt; I could simulate an LLM by hand without
understanding why it's outputting a
certain word rather than another No, no,
you you couldn't because you could have
a computer to help you with the with the
donkey work of that. You could say, "See
what would be the result of this train
of thought and it would go, zip." Well,
then then it turns out kill all humans.
Okay, now we've now we've narrowed it
down to one train of thought. Let's go
halfway along and and so on. You you
could by interval having you could find
out where where the difference arose
and
&gt;&gt; right. I wouldn't understand the reason
for that difference. I could I could do
test lots of different prompts and see
which outputs get all humans without
ever having a good understanding of
which kind what characterizes the kind
of prompt that leads to to that or what
kind of internal
&gt;&gt; I'm not thinking of um sorry may maybe I
I said the wrong thing when when I
likened it to um performing touring
machine computation or whatever. I mean
following along its moral reasoning.
following along the starting with the
problem that it has or had and ending up
with the conclusion and following along
its moral reasoning
&gt;&gt; down to whatever level you know if if it
begins with its qualia or whatever you
know including the qualia and then
following that along using machine to to
jump over the the
non-aggi
components of its AGI thinking
&gt;&gt; and then see where we start to differ.
&gt;&gt; So, [clears throat] and if we find for
example that that differ because it well
this would be better with an alien. So,
it it it is a carnivore and it's really
deeply into its motivations that it it
has to eat
um what whatever I mean other other
entities. Um, then we could see then
then we could say to it, look, you're
only saying this because your genes say
you have to eat things. And it would
say, yes, but that's that's well and
good. That's how things should be. And
then we we could say to it, but you're
only saying that because uh your genes
say so. It's different from all the
other reasons you've given along all
that that chain of reasoning, your your
moral considerations. None of those
involve anything like that. This one
does. Why should this one override the
others?
And it might say,
well, because it tastes good. And then
again, you'd say that that's a different
kind of argument from the one you've
been using all the way up to now. like
um I was just reading day before
yesterday about um conversation between
Mark Twain
um and Winston Churchill when Winston
Churchill was a young man and he was
doing a book tour of America and he was
introduced to Mark Twain who was quite
old and Churchill was quite young and
they were arguing about the whether the
British Empire was a moral thing and
Mark Twain was saying that it was
extremely immoral
And um Churchill tried his best to put
up an argument and then he says in his
book
I would finally he beat me back to my
fortress my country right or wrong. Now
see, [laughter]
Churchill was there saying that that he
was beaten back to irrationality
&gt;&gt; and and Mark Twain he and Mark Twain
both considered that Churchill had been
defeated in that argument.
But um I think Churchill the bottom line
was that Churchill was right and that
the real reason he couldn't think of a
better argument is that he didn't have
um a better theory of morality than he
actually had. But
&gt;&gt; I mean when he Go on sorry
&gt;&gt; well he he he he did change after that.
He he he changed his justification which
often happens when when people have to
abandon a form of morality. They they
change the justification before they
change the bottom line.
And so um
Churchill then by the end it was about
it hinged on the bore war.
And um uh by the way, it's interesting
that neither of them made any mention of
the black people in South Africa. It was
all about the the rights of British
people and the rights of of Bo. And it's
obviously it it just didn't occur to
them that anyone else was involved.
&gt;&gt; Um
&gt;&gt; uh so they
they were able to affect each other.
they were able to make each other uh
rethink their ideas and they were able
to see separately
whether an argument made sense or
whether they were right.
Uh and um obviously it there's there's
no law of the universe that says that
when that happens you will always go for
the argument which is probably quite
quite a good thing because our arguments
are not always better than our uh
intuition about what is right. So
&gt;&gt; yeah go ahead. For for example, I I
believe that causing animals suffering
is wrong. And yeah, I still eat meat
occasionally. So my moral deliberations
have not in fact changed my actions, at
least not wholly.
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So you you have a a conflict in
your moral theories. So your your moral
theories. Uh so for a start it's not
true that you um
um that you let one override the other
because you have decided that the best
thing for you to do is to eat meat. It's
not that your
qualia have told you to do that.
&gt;&gt; It's your theory of what
&gt;&gt; I don't know. They're asking pretty
strongly. [laughter]
Uh, I don't think so because if somebody
if if a doctor told you that you that
you had six weeks to live unless you
stop eating meat, you'd stop.
&gt;&gt; I think that's because I take my own
suffering more seriously than animals
suffer.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, it it uh it's not that.
&gt;&gt; It's not that. It's that you you take
reason more seriously than qualia.
But but there is also a reasonable
theory that says if we act on the maxim
of always suppressing alqualia we will
fail to take into account the inexplicit
knowledge that is in them.
&gt;&gt; Uh could you explain that?
&gt;&gt; So the the the knowledge that we have
expressed in words and mathematical
theorems and scientific theories that's
only the tip of the iceberg.
Um to understand something you have to
have um a lot more theoretical
underpinning than just that. just to
know why
logic is valid and to to uh think why
when you are justified in taking
experience into account and when you
aren't and and what it I'm I'm trying to
trying to explain in words that not
everything can be explained in words. So
there's only certain [laughter]
distance I can go along those lines. But
&gt;&gt; right
&gt;&gt; but uh my usual example is that we don't
know the meanings of words. We don't
even know the meanings of any words um
without some inexplicit ideas because if
if all the meanings of words were
expressed in words then that would be a
circular definition.
So we so we we um
uh there's a lot of knowledge in our
inexplicit ideas
and um if if we have a rule for always
overriding them when they conflict with
explicit ideas then we'll be throwing
away most of the knowledge that we have.
the the better thing to do is is to when
when we encounter such a conflict is to
think about think critically about who
is right and probably they're both
wrong. So we can
&gt;&gt; I think my my qualia my positive qualia
when eating meat have I would argue
approximately zero moral content.
&gt;&gt; So I don't see that they're telling me
anything.
you supposing somebody decided
um like
Dr. Shreber in the 19th century decided
that it's best for children to grow up
never being comfortable. You always had
to make sure that they were somehow
uncomfortable that they didn't get to
eat what they wanted and um they didn't
get to sit in comfortable chairs. if
they asked for something then they
definitely shouldn't get that thing and
so on.
&gt;&gt; He was wildly successful in Germany.
&gt;&gt; Um and Alice Miller thinks that that
that's that that caused Hitler. I I I
don't think that but I think it was
morally wrong and I think it was
practically wrong but the the practical
wrongness was not so obvious that it
that stood out for people at the time
for decades when this when this was
tried.
&gt;&gt; Um so and it it was powerful people
against powerless people. So the the
issue of needing to come to a consensus
didn't arise. So um people people did
that uh and it's wrong for the same
reason that you should not force
yourself to stop eating meat. It's
exactly the same.
I think um let let's go back to this uh
argument with the alien um that if there
was some moral conflict then we could
simulate them simulate their moral
cognitive processes and say to them oh
well you're only saying this because
that and that's arbitrary such as their
their genetic information or whatever
kind of way they inherit information
from ancestors.
um
that would take a long time. And if we
were doing this with with AGIS, it's not
uh it's not a trivial process to try and
uh
disentangle from the enormous amount of
computations they're doing. the the
meaningful parts well it's all
meaningful but the the parts that can be
passed in our kind of language our
ontology uh to then communicate with
them on a common ground re reasons I
mean reasons are not in the zeros and
ones directly we have to interpret them
as reasons so this sounds like one a big
engineering challenge and two something
that would take an awful lot of time so
then the question would be like would
the AGI
motivated to wait around while we did
this. Uh wouldn't it just if we have
diverging values and this is going to
take the next 10 years to figure out
think oh well too bad it's going to take
10 years.
&gt;&gt; This AGI is going to start off with our
values presumably because we we are the
ones who brought it up from from
scratch. So it started off with our
values and in trying to improve them, it
came to values that seem to us
very off and we we can't and and when it
tries to explain to us why it came up
with those values,
&gt;&gt; then we don't get it. We just don't get
it. We think it must be it that's made a
mistake.
&gt;&gt; Um this is the situation that the human
race has always been in and especially
has been in since the Enlightenment.
This is the um problem of how to get on
with teenagers.
Um people people have been complaining
for centuries and in fact millennia
although it's got worse and worse since
the enlightenment that that teenagers in
this generation are uniquely bad
and and they are uniquely bad for
basically mechanical reasons
uh because of their hormones
um because of their um uh social media
media because of their mobile phones and
so on. And and so we want to use force
to settle the issue. And that is a bad
idea because when it is when they are
worse, they will be worse for some
reason which seems like let's suppose
for the sake of argument that they are
worse that their values are worse. Then
they will be worse because they seemed
better but in fact aren't.
And that is a point of view that is
extremely close to ours and uh we have a
moral duty since we have
decanted them into a world that has this
problem this inherent problem in it. It
is up to us to try to solve this.
Um, it could be that we will fail to
solve it and that civilization will end
after another generation because the
AGIS will destroy us all. What will not
happen is that they'll go on living
happily despite well actually even that
could happen. It could be that they
destroy us, go on living happily and
then realize that they shouldn't have
destroyed us and then go on living
happily.
&gt;&gt; Right? This is this is all very you know
that's that's that's
in the same category of artificiality as
saying we may find a reason that dark
energy is going to burn us all up next
year.
It could be could be that our theories
of physics are wrong in exactly that way
in which case we're doomed. But as I
said before
there is no such cloud on the horizon.
All the things that are cited as
evidence for that, like
the teenagers seem to like their mobile
phones better than their school lessons,
are evidence in the other direction.
So, uh, as I say, we can't you can't
prove that we're not doomed. But, uh, I
will be very surprised if we're doomed
by that method.
I think a comet impacting the earth is
is much more much more plausible.
&gt;&gt; I see. There's there's there's never a
limit on the size of error you can make
even in moral thinking. Yes.
&gt;&gt; And so AGIS could also make a mistake.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
&gt;&gt; Decide to wipe us out.
&gt;&gt; But then eventually because of their
infinite explanatory reach, if they
don't wipe themselves out, they'll
eventually realize they made a mistake
in wiping us out. Yes.
&gt;&gt; I see. Um,
you mentioned that they would start off
with our values and therefore in a sense
they would be like our descendants
&gt;&gt; and that assuming their values if they
diverged from ours are necessarily worse
would be like assuming our descendants
not even one not even 10,000 years in
the future but a single generation are
worse. Um
&gt;&gt; I I agree with this and I think if we
did manage if AGIS did in fact start off
with our values then they should be
allowed to evolve their values hopefully
in discussion with us just as we are
allowed to to modify ours. But then the
question of whether AIs would in fact
start off with our values, that looks an
awful lot like the alignment problem of
successfully imbuing our values into
AIS. And I don't see that we would
necessarily succeed in that. I think
it's possible we could create universal
explainers, if I'm using your language
correctly, that do not start off with
our values. They might start off much
worse than our values. uh and therefore
&gt;&gt; their their values will be caused by the
initial state of their computation.
&gt;&gt; Yes. it and um I don't see ho how how
how that could possibly be done except
by making them contentless or almost
contentless or I mean just like babies
grow up with start start off with no
theories of physics or mathematics or
morality
um and they they they
get all their theories by conjecture and
criticism. If we start them off, if we
start an AGI off by being the equivalent
of a of a 21-year-old human,
um, then they'll all be the same and
we'll lose all the benefit of having
one.
So,
&gt;&gt; don't babies start off with the moral
theory that they should get what they
want.
&gt;&gt; Everyone else be damned.
&gt;&gt; Um,
no. Uh, I mean, some people think that
humans start off like that, but I I
think that's that's um basically
impossible. And even if it were true,
they would the main thing that the main
thing that a baby or an AGI is doing is
it's trying to solve problems. It's
trying to create the solutions to
problems by changing its existing ideas.
What it's initial existing ideas are is
somewhat irrelevant.
um because because of the G and because
of the creative and person and all those
constellation of properties
um they they can improve on their ideas.
So if we started them off as a baby with
arbitrary ideas, you know, if we started
off with chimp type ideas or whatever,
as long as they had human type
um creative thinking, they would soon
lose their chimp like ideas. And I mean,
you think that it could have a long-term
consequence that eventually it'll cause
them to want to wipe out the world or or
something, but I I as I said, I I don't
think so. uh and I think far easier and
more efficient thing is for them to
start out with the just a basic
operating system.
um that allow that that uh allows them
to interact with the world and thereby
acquire problems have expect they have
expectations which can be violated
um where they can go choose the
direction that they can go and improve
them and they will be doing that by
interacting with the with the human
humans who are bringing them up and also
with the rest of society.
Um, now if you started them off with the
values of the Chinese Communist Party,
then we might be in trouble. Um, I don't
know. I don't know what what happens if
you maybe such a person would in would
immediately think there's something
really wrong with the way I'm thinking.
Uh, can I can I find a better way of
thinking? Um, I don't know. But we
wouldn't do that, would we?
Well, I I I think my argument would be
that we we don't know how to reliably
implant any values, good, bad,
&gt;&gt; right? Reli right. Reliably is the last
thing we want
&gt;&gt; because we want to we want to uh implant
creativity. We want if if if the initial
state is unreliable and gets changed and
that that's fine. That's good. That's
what we're aiming for. We're aiming to
give it the G property,
&gt;&gt; which [clears throat] it can't have if
it's got, for example, alignment built
in
or Marxism built in.
So, so in a sense,
so maybe your argument is that it
doesn't really so much matter what
values it would start off with, provided
it has this creative ability to to
question moral explanations and make
improvement on them,
&gt;&gt; then it will come to similar conclusions
as we will or we'll be able to talk it
through.
&gt;&gt; Yes. Or we'll fail and die. Okay.
[laughter]
&gt;&gt; But but that that is the same as if we
were talking about astronomy. I mean
that's the same with all human
knowledge.
uh that it that we can er
&gt;&gt; we can er and there's a limit to how
large a mistake we can make
&gt;&gt; right because it's possible that an AI
could start off with what we would
consider the wrong values and would
eventually come to better values uh
values that we would also understand as
better but that that would take an
extremely long time and in the meantime
it would go via some values that we
would think of as
and would lead to
&gt;&gt; taking us on the inside as it were
without ever passing through the values
that we have.
&gt;&gt; Uh yes. Yeah.
&gt;&gt; But it would be interacting with us
&gt;&gt; continuously at least through the first
part of this until it got to you know as
as powerful a morality as we have. But
but in another way it would be
interacting with us and there'd be some
reason why it was different. Uh it it
would be um the fact that we had
different values from it would be um
uh a gift a gift from from pure
mathematics that there could be such a
thing because the first thing we would
do is to examine these values that it
had and the first thing it would do is
examine the values that we have and we
could learn from each other. Maybe
there's some good in each.
Why why would we why would that be the
first thing we'd both do?
&gt;&gt; If if if you if you find in in some
field of knowledge, if you find someone
who is who has a lot of knowledge in
that field but has come to very
different conclusions to you, then you
want to know why. H
so this is I suppose what we've been
discussing here really is in AI safety
at least is what's called the
orthogonality thesis. This idea that
capabilities to to solve uh
technological or physical problems can
be completely independent from which
values you actually have. And I it see
uh I hope I'm not putting words in your
mouth when I say you don't believe the
orthogonality [laughter] thesis
&gt;&gt; in [clears throat] spades. I don't
believe that. Uh there there uh it it
seems to come from some earlier form of
philosophy of science like empiricism or
something that that uh thinks that moral
knowledge is some kind of inherently
different thing from factual knowledge
or from Hume perhaps. um
&gt;&gt; uh you but but um I think anyone who
believes that ought to read Bronoski
&gt;&gt; uh science and human values and and th
those little thin pamphlets
&gt;&gt; books that he wrote.
&gt;&gt; I must have I saw a tweet of yours that
that said, "Read this and you'll never
believe the orthogonality thesis
[laughter] again." Ah,
&gt;&gt; and I I found it quite hard to make the
connection between the pamphlet and the
orthogonality thesis.
&gt;&gt; Okay. Well, I'm sorry about that. Well,
[laughter]
&gt;&gt; I can't remember tweeting that, but it
sounds like it was Bronovski and it was
Yeah. And um so he makes a number of
arguments about why scientific values
and moral values and also aesthetic
values are inseparable.
And uh one of the nicer arguments in uh
one of the mo most convincing arguments
I have found about scientific and moral
theories is that you can't do science
unless you subscribe to certain moral
values such as
um tolerance. Because science can't pro
progress very far without a scientific
community and a scientific community
can't progress unless it is tolerant of
deviant theories.
So right uh so the the never mind
deviant moral theories just deviant
scientific theories.
So um if you if you want to be tolerant
of those you need to subscribe to the
value of tolerance in science at least.
So you know you're tolerant in the in
the seminar room and then when you go
outside you you push aside everybody and
and in in the queue for lunch,
&gt;&gt; right? But but unless you obey the rules
inside the seminar room, society is
going to gr science is going to grind to
a halt.
&gt;&gt; So that that's one of Bronovski's
arguments and is very perceptive. I
think it's very true in in real life
because I think that
&gt;&gt; the conduct of scientists in seminar
rooms is much more moral than the
conduct of scientists outside seminar
rooms.
Yeah, I I Okay, I see how that would put
a crack in the orthogonality thesis. At
least those values and those abilities
cannot come apart. The value of
tolerance of new ideas and the people
expressing them.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; And and the progress of science. But uh
it's it's you could still say the world
or this is a bad theory, but you could
say the orthogonality thesis holds
except for that. Yeah. Well, I I didn't
say that was Bronoski's only argument.
&gt;&gt; Okay. [laughter]
&gt;&gt; Another argument of his is is that
another value that that science depends
on is respect for truth.
So um again some people would say
science is only valuable if it is
directed towards
um the good of mankind or or something
or directed towards um um the
improvement of the economy or or
something like that. And um it's it's
now almost a truism that
science constrained in that way not only
does not approach truth very far, it
doesn't approve it doesn't improve the
value of the economy or human welfare or
anything that the the only way science
can improve is if if people are seeking
the truth,
&gt;&gt; not the ideas that best do something
else.
and the truth about morality.
Okay, again I I can't say in in
principle that there can't be a morality
that says you know we should pursue the
truth in mathematics and in science but
not in morality
not in other morality apart from the
morality of mathematics and the morality
of science.
Uh
at the end of these arguments I've
always got to say yeah it could happen.
Mhm.
&gt;&gt; Um but I I see no sign of it and all the
things that are held up as examples of
how it could happen are are examples of
the opposite.
&gt;&gt; One one example often brought up in the
orthogonality thesis is this idea of
Hitler that he he was very capable but
had completely aborant values.
on your worldview if Hitler was given
enough time uh to think that he would
eventually realize what he was doing was
wrong.
&gt;&gt; Well, um
if I think it would go thousands of
times faster if he could be imprisoned
somewhere where people could talk to him
and not allowed to make wars.
Um but yes, there's there's no reason to
believe that that uh Hitler was not an
AGI, was not a GI.
Um I think people who lose generality
um in their thinking are very noticeably
different.
um
they do things like like um
not speak and and um or just do exactly
the same thing over and over again. I'm
not saying that people who don't speak
or do things over and over again are not
gis. Usually they are. But the ones who
aren't G gis will do things that require
no creativity. Even tying one's
shoelaces in the way that humans do
requires general intelligence.
&gt;&gt; Apes can't do it. They can they can tie
it so long as the laces are are, you
know, initially always in the same
configuration and so on, but they the
apes can't understand what laces do.
&gt;&gt; They can only mimic and mimic the
non-purposeful parts of the action.
&gt;&gt; Yes. Yes.
Exactly.
&gt;&gt; Um, but Hitler could tie his shoelaces,
I assume.
&gt;&gt; Exactly. So that that's why I think
that's why I think he was a GI.
&gt;&gt; Oh, was sorry I misheard.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; Okay. Um
Okay. So GIS can be evil, [laughter] but
they'll eventually figure out that
they're being evil. And it could go a
lot quicker if they're talking to other
people. uh they're in dialogue just like
science goes much quicker if you're in
dialogue with other scientists.
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
&gt;&gt; Um and in the meantime we can restrict
their actions uh to make sure they don't
do too much damage.
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; Okay. So it could be justified to
restrict an AGI until we were sure it
was on a similar path to us with its
values.
&gt;&gt; Uh it's the other way around. it would
be justified to restrict it if we were
sure that it was wasn't on a similar
path.
&gt;&gt; I see. You don't want to restrict it
until you're sure that it is.
&gt;&gt; This is a fundamental principle of the
enlightenment.
&gt;&gt; Uhhuh.
&gt;&gt; That that innocent until proved guilty.
&gt;&gt; Right. Right.
I suppose I'm just nervous that
humans I do think our values are large
are at least start off very informed by
the kind of intuitions we're born with.
I mean we are born with a kind of
intuitive physics of object permanence
and well okay that does actually come
later but there are some very basic
notions
&gt;&gt; that that are in built and humans start
off with with the same kind of record
&gt;&gt; and they lose them very fast
&gt;&gt; because they're wrong
&gt;&gt; un yeah unless they're true in which
case they keep them [laughter] but but
uh it's a feature of gene and meme
evolution that once something can be
taken over by memes. There's no more
selection pressure for it to be encoded
in genes. So that decays that that um
thing decays and yeah I mean when when I
was a child I used to read uh comics
&gt;&gt; uh DC comics and Marvel comics and so on
and the entire adult world was trying to
stop me and [laughter]
&gt;&gt; I'm sorry
&gt;&gt; trying because they according to their
best theories it was it was harming my
mind
&gt;&gt; right
&gt;&gt; and they are wrong for they were wrong
for the same reason that people have
always been wrong about this and the
same reason that they are wrong about
this. out
&gt;&gt; one last point before we we finish.
[laughter] I want to hear your your your
take on. [gasps] So a AGIS can be can
have different values and become enemies
of civilization just like humans can.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
&gt;&gt; Their theories, their understanding
about how to solve problems. Abilities
in different domains
can progress at different rates.
And with humans, we don't progress at
the same rate in different domains, but
there is a kind of distribution that we
follow. We don't diverge arbitrarily
much. Maybe in theory, we do, but in
practice, compared to all possible
minds, we're at least clustered more
tightly,
&gt;&gt; I guess. Although my progress in chess
uh and in in playing the piano and in
physics
are pretty different by many orders of
magnitude,
&gt;&gt; but okay, that's that's still not as as
big a difference as you could think
think of in principle. Yeah.
&gt;&gt; Yeah. [snorts]
So when we when we produce new people,
we're selecting from that kind of
distribution. Um uh
When we produce new people,
um, we're we're giving them the same
infinite ability.
Once they're people or they're they're
all the same in regard to their infinite
potential and they're all the same in in
regard to, as Papa says, in regard to
their infinite ignorance.
So, in that sense, they're all the same.
They may all have [clears throat]
slightly different qualia but that's
going to be u soon soon forgotten about
as they form their ideas.
&gt;&gt; So I mean they're they're equal in terms
of their reach in these different
domains that they're all infinite but
&gt;&gt; yes
&gt;&gt; for practical purposes they will
progress at different rates in these
different
&gt;&gt; in different subject. Yeah. Yeah.
&gt;&gt; Yes. So if you if we build artificial
minds, they might be much
they might be outside this cluster of
different rates at which humans progress
in different domains. And so it's
possible that you could have some a mind
that makes much more rapid progress in
technology than in morality.
&gt;&gt; Uh yes.
uh just as with humans
&gt;&gt; right but it would be there's a larger
with humans it's from the same cluster
whereas from with AI it's
&gt;&gt; no I don't think they start with any
cluster
&gt;&gt; okay
&gt;&gt; yeah I I think the the the difference
between different babies is negligible
&gt;&gt; in terms of what they can achieve in
their life and how fast they'll go in
different domains
&gt;&gt; the difference in their starting ideas
&gt;&gt; Mhm. the like when they start they all
want to drink milk and and uh turn
towards sounds and you know whatever
their initial program is.
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
&gt;&gt; Um most of what baby animals can do they
have lost because because evolution has
decided it is better to let ideas decide
that rather than genes.
So most of those genes have but they
they have a bare minimum
&gt;&gt; uh genetic behaviors to make sure they
don't just die
um before they can you know
reach for things or whatever whatever
babies have to do first.
&gt;&gt; But uh the diversity is going to come
because they become different when
they're creative. So as soon as they are
soon certainly as soon as they're old
enough to speak, they will have
interests that are different from each
other and they are very strongly
different from each other. So that some
of them will enjoy doing things that
that others hate doing.
So um uh they're very different and but
they they they
converge
because they have access to other people
and to society
and um they converge to society partly
because th those are the raw material
for theories. you know, may as well go
for that theory if there's no other
theory going. But also because there's a
lot of truth in those theories.
&gt;&gt; So, uh, then they can become different
and then the difference will
show itself in some kind of conflict.
Um, but it it um it it won't, you know,
I I don't know. And uh it could be that
we're all doomed because of some glitch
in the fabric of reality. But but uh I
think the most likely thing is that they
will differ because one of them likes
playing the violin and the other one
likes playing the piano and the other
one likes doing physics and and the the
other likes um watching cartoons and and
so on. And uh all of them well many of
them will at some point say no I don't
want to and most of them will be saying
that about a different thing.
So and if they're all saying it about
the same thing then we ought to think
that maybe we're wrong. H
I I suppose that the the the last niggle
I have is um
it seems possible that we could get a
human that
just vastly
surpasses our ability at technological
progress and yet is
um not stunted. That would be the wrong
word. it would still be have unlimited
moral potential for moral progress, but
it just goes much more slowly. It chugs
along in that respect. And that seems
quite unlikely to happen with humans um
because we've seen 9 billion of them.
Well, many more now and we haven't
really seen that. Whereas with AIS, it
seems much harder to rule out that we
would have this.
&gt;&gt; We've seen the reverse.
We've seen uh people have people come up
with with either very good or very bad
moral theories.
&gt;&gt; Um
and if they're moral theories, then
they're going to come into conflict with
the surrounding theories. And then
you're going to have,
you know, Martin Luther uh nailing up uh
95 thesis on the door. And um and then
that's going to cause a a debate and in
a more decent society than what they had
then.
&gt;&gt; Um this is not going to lead to
violence.
Uh the fact that it led to violence then
just just shows you how how much
progress we've made since then
&gt;&gt; in the west.
&gt;&gt; In the west.
&gt;&gt; Um but you're going to say what? Yes.
But what if he's more different from our
society than Luther was from the
Catholic Church?
&gt;&gt; Yeah, it could. And again, you know, we
and we couldn't. And and and
we we don't catch it. He and we don't
bother to talk about it while they're
still while we're still on the same page
in regard to being able to talk to each
other about it. And then suppose that in
the in the case that he's better he or
she is better uh or it I don't know what
what the custom will be by the time we
have AGIS
um will um be better at technology
before we before before it or we notice
that something is going wrong
uh with its morality
&gt;&gt; and and [clears throat] it it builds a
hydrogen bomb or builds ICBMs and
hydrogen bombs in its backyard and
before anyone notices it's press the
fire button and and um uh I still
haven't managed to make a scenario that
could work even even in in terms of
grotesque [clears throat]
science fiction. I mean even that
wouldn't end civilization.
No, it's quite hard to end civilization
[laughter]
for good. And that that is is something
that differs from, you know, what's
what's imaginable by far less than the
wars of the 20th century. They they were
much more destructive than than a person
building an ICBMs and H bombs in their
backyard.
&gt;&gt; Well, we're going to make mistakes
with this just like with every other
technology.
Yeah. Yeah. And I think that's one thing
I misunderstood when I first encountered
your views. It sounded like you were
saying we inex inexurably make progress
&gt;&gt; and things inexraably get better. And it
took me a while to realize no, you're
not at all saying that.
&gt;&gt; We make mistakes. There's no no limit on
the size of mistake we can make.
&gt;&gt; But it's best to keep going and keep
trying. [clears throat]
That's a there's less existential risk
by keeping to make progress keep by
keeping making progress than there is
&gt;&gt; absolutely
&gt;&gt; eliminating progress. [clears throat]
&gt;&gt; Not making progress makes um is the
existential risk that that that makes
[clears throat] um uh doom certain.
&gt;&gt; Mhm. Because of the asteroid.
&gt;&gt; Yes. Or or or the more likely the thing
that we don't know about. Yeah. Yeah.
&gt;&gt; Well, I've I've kept you well over the
time I [laughter] I asked you for, so
I'll I'll I'll wrap it up now. But uh I
I have I really really enjoyed the
conversation. It's been so much fun
having you on. And as expected, I got
out of my prepared opening book almost
immediately. [laughter]