I'm sure that,
throughout the 100,000-odd years
of our species' existence
and even before,
our ancestors looked up at the night sky
and wondered what stars are --
wondering, therefore,
how to explain what they saw
in terms of things unseen.
OK, so, most people only wondered
that occasionally, like today,
in breaks from whatever
normally preoccupied them.
But what normally preoccupied them
also involved yearning to know.
They wished they knew
how to prevent their food supply
from sometimes failing,
and how they could rest
when they were tired
without risking starvation,
be warmer, cooler, safer,
in less pain.
I bet those prehistoric cave artists
would have loved to know
how to draw better.
(Laughter)
In every aspect of their lives,
they wished for progress, just as we do.
But they failed, almost
completely, to make any.
They didn't know how to.
Discoveries like fire happened so rarely
that, from an individual's point of view,
the world never improved.
Nothing new was learned.
The first clue to the origin of starlight
happened as recently as 1899:
radioactivity.
And within 40 years,
physicists discovered
the whole explanation,
expressed, as usual, in elegant symbols.
But never mind the symbols.
Think how many discoveries they represent.
Nuclei and nuclear reactions, of course.
But isotopes,
particles of electricity,
antimatter,
neutrinos,
the conversion of mass
to energy -- that's E=mc2 --
gamma rays,
transmutation.
That ancient dream that had
always eluded the alchemists
was achieved through these same theories
that explained starlight
and other ancient mysteries
and new, unexpected phenomena.
That all that, discovered in 40 years,
had not been in the previous
hundred thousand
was not for lack of thinking
about stars and all those other
urgent problems they had.
They even arrived at answers,
such as myths,
that dominated their lives,
yet bore almost
no resemblance to the truth.
The tragedy of that protracted stagnation
isn't sufficiently recognized, I think.
These were people with brains
of essentially the same design
that eventually did discover
all those things.
But that ability to make progress
remained almost unused,
until the event that revolutionized
the human condition
and changed the universe.
Or so we should hope,
because that event
was the scientific revolution,
ever since which our knowledge
of the physical world
and of how to adapt it to our wishes
has been growing relentlessly.
Now, what had changed?
What were people now doing
for the first time
that made that difference
between stagnation
and rapid, open-ended discovery?
How to make that difference
is surely the most important
universal truth
that it's possible to know.
And worryingly, there's no consensus
about what it is.
So, I'll tell you.
(Laughter)
But I'll have to backtrack a little first.
Before the scientific revolution,
they believed that everything
important, knowable,
was already known,
enshrined in ancient
writings, institutions
and in some genuinely
useful rules of thumb --
which were, however, entrenched as dogmas,
along with many falsehoods.
So, they believed that knowledge
came from authorities
that actually knew very little.
And therefore,
progress depended
on learning how to reject
the authority of learned men,
the priests, traditions and rulers,
which is why the scientific revolution
had to have a wider context:
the Enlightenment, a revolution
in how people sought knowledge,
trying not to rely on authority.
"Take no one's word for it."
But that can't be
what made the difference.
Authorities had been rejected
before, many times.
And that rarely, if ever,
caused anything
like the scientific revolution.
At the time, what they thought
distinguished science
was a radical idea about things unseen,
known as empiricism --
all knowledge derives from the senses.
Well, we've seen that that can't be true.
It did help by promoting
observation and experiment.
But, from the outset,
it was obvious that there was something
horribly wrong with it.
Knowledge comes from the senses?
In what language?
Certainly not the language of mathematics,
in which, Galileo rightly said,
the book of nature is written.
Look at the world.
You don't see equations
carved on the mountainsides.
If you did, it would be because
people had carved them.
By the way, why don't we do that?
(Laughter)
What's wrong with us?
Empiricism is inadequate
because, well, scientific theories
explain the seen in terms of the unseen.
And the unseen, you have to admit,
doesn't come to us through the senses.
We don't see those nuclear
reactions in stars.
We don't see the origin of species.
We don't see the curvature of space-time,
and other universes.
But we know about those things.
How?
Well, the classic empiricist
answer is induction --
the unseen resembles the seen.
But it doesn't.
You know what the clinching evidence was
that space-time is curved?
It was a photograph -- not of space-time,
but of an eclipse, with a dot
there rather than there.
And the evidence for evolution?
Some rocks and some finches.
And parallel universes?
Again: dots there
rather than there, on a screen.
What we see in all these cases
bears no resemblance to the reality
that we conclude is responsible --
only a long chain of theoretical reasoning
and interpretation connects them.
"Ah!" say creationists.
"So you admit it's all interpretation.
No one's ever seen evolution.
We see rocks.
You have your interpretation.
We have ours.
Yours comes from guesswork;
ours, from the Bible."
But what creationist
and empiricists both ignore
is that, in that sense,
no one's ever seen a Bible either,
that the eye only detects light,
which we don't perceive.
Brains only detect nerve impulses.
And they don't perceive even those
as what they really are,
namely electrical crackles.
So we perceive nothing
as what it really is.
Our connection to reality
is never just perception.
It's always, as Karl Popper put it,
theory-laden.
Scientific knowledge
isn't derived from anything.
Like all knowledge,
it's conjectural, guesswork,
tested by observation,
not derived from it.
So, were testable conjectures
the great innovation
that opened the intellectual prison gates?
No, contrary to what's usually said,
testability is common
in myths and all sorts of other
irrational modes of thinking.
Any crank claiming the sun
will go out next Tuesday
has got a testable prediction.
Consider the ancient Greek myth
explaining seasons.
Hades, god of the underworld,
kidnaps Persephone, the goddess of spring,
and negotiates a forced marriage contract,
requiring her to return regularly,
and lets her go.
And each year,
she is magically compelled to return.
And her mother, Demeter,
goddess of the earth,
is sad, and makes it cold and barren.
That myth is testable.
If winter is caused by Demeter's sadness,
then it must happen everywhere
on earth simultaneously.
So if the ancient Greeks had only known
that Australia is at its warmest
when Demeter is at her saddest ...
(Laughter)
they'd have known
that their theory is false.
(Laughter)
So, what was wrong with that myth
and with all prescientific thinking?
And what, then, made
that momentous difference?
I think there's one thing
you have to care about
and that implies testability,
the scientific method,
the Enlightenment and everything.
And here's the crucial thing:
there is such a thing
as a defect in a story.
I don't just mean a logical defect.
I mean a bad explanation.
What does that mean?
Well, an explanation is an assertion
about what's there, unseen,
that accounts for what's seen;
because the explanatory role
of Persephone's marriage contract
could be played equally well
by infinitely many other ad hoc entities.
Why a marriage contract
and not any other reason
for regular annual action?
Here's one: Persephone wasn't released.
She escaped, and returns every spring
to take revenge on Hades,
with her spring powers.
She cools his domain with spring air,
venting heat up to the surface,
creating summer.
That accounts for the same
phenomena as the original myth.
It's equally testable.
Yet what it asserts about reality
is, in many ways, the opposite.
And that's possible
because the details of the original myth
are unrelated to seasons,
except via the myth itself.
This easy variability
is the sign of a bad explanation,
because, without a functional reason
to prefer one of countless variants,
advocating one of them
in preference to the others
is irrational.
So, for the essence of what makes
the difference to enable progress,
seek good explanations,
the ones that can't be easily varied,
while still explaining the phenomena.
Now our current explanation of seasons
is that the Earth's axis
is tilted like that,
so each hemisphere tilts
towards the sun for half the year,
and away for the other half.
[Not to scale!]
Better put that up.
(Laughter)
That's a good explanation:
hard to vary,
because every detail
plays a functional role.
For instance, we know,
independently of seasons,
that surfaces tilted away
from radiant heat are heated less,
and that a spinning sphere, in space,
points in a constant direction.
And the tilt also explains
the sun's angle of elevation
at different times of year,
and predicts that the seasons will be
out of phase in the two hemispheres.
If they'd been observed in phase,
the theory would have been refuted.
But now, the fact that it's also
a good explanation, hard to vary,
makes the crucial difference.
If the ancient Greeks had found out
about seasons in Australia,
they could have easily
varied their myth to predict that.
For instance, when Demeter's upset,
she banishes heat from her vicinity
into the other hemisphere,
where it makes summer.
So, being proved wrong by observation
and changing their theory accordingly
still wouldn't have got the ancient Greeks
one jot closer to understanding seasons,
because their explanation
was bad -- easy to vary.
And it's only when an explanation is good
that it even matters
whether it's testable.
If the axis-tilt theory had been refuted,
its defenders would have had
nowhere to go.
No easily implemented change
could make that tilt cause
the same seasons in both hemispheres.
The search for hard-to-vary explanations
is the origin of all progress.
It's the basic regulating principle
of the Enlightenment.
So, in science, two false
approaches blight progress.
One's well-known: untestable theories.
But the more important one
is explanationless theories.
Whenever you're told that some existing
statistical trend will continue
but you aren't given a hard-to-vary
account of what causes that trend,
you're being told a wizard did it.
When you are told
that carrots have human rights
because they share half our genes,
but not how gene percentages
confer rights -- wizard.
When someone announces
that the nature-nurture debate
has been settled
because there's evidence that a given
percentage of our political opinions
are genetically inherited,
but they don't explain
how genes cause opinions,
they've settled nothing.
They're saying that our opinions
are caused by wizards,
and presumably, so are their own.
(Laughter)
That the truth consists
of hard-to-vary assertions about reality
is the most important fact
about the physical world.
It's a fact that is itself unseen,
yet impossible to vary.
Thank you.
(Applause)